<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root>
    <!--The identification of the recipient as an 'unnamed loved one' is presumptious. There is evidence that these letters are written wit a romantic partner of close friend in mind.-->
    <letter sender="Marian Baldwin" recipient="unnamed loved one">
        <header>[<author>Letter from <person name="Marian Baldwin">Marian Baldwin</person></author>,
                    <date><month when="June">June</month> 30, <year when="1917"
            >1917</year></date>]</header>

        <location name="La Touraine">On Board La Touraine,</location>

        <date when="6/30/1917"><month>June</month> 30, <year>1917</year>.</date>

        <paragraph n="1">Even now that we are out of sight of land, it seems impossible that I am
            actually off to France and, for the first time in my life, traveling alone. Everything
            has happened so quickly since the American Fund for French Wounded found an opening for
            me in Paris that I suppose I am still somewhat dazed and bewildered. The fact that I
            don't know what it will all be like and that I can't look ahead makes it easier to be
            happy and live in the present. Of course I have had a bit of a taste in New York of the
            work that the A. F. F. W. is doing but its <location name="A.F.F.W Headwuarters"
                >Headquarters in Paris</location> will be different in some ways I
            fancy.</paragraph>

        <paragraph n="2">I can't get over how lucky I am to have this chance for I realize how few
            girls of my age are getting across, and I understood the grit and pluck which made you
            encourage me on my great adventure and send me along a path which has proved so
            dangerous of late.</paragraph>

        <paragraph n="3">As we drifted down the river, in the sunset glow with two absurd tugs
            puffing alongside, I know that many eyes were moist and that the same thought was in all
            our minds. How many of this ship's company will see that sky-line again! It was very
            quiet, no one spoke much, and, little by little, the glow faded from the sky and one
            star after another appeared. I knew that you would be looking at those same stars down
            in Lakewood and that your thoughts and prayers were the same that filled my heart at
            that moment. Somehow distance does not separate, after all.</paragraph>
        <!--Judging by the last two paragraphs, it appears that this document is a letter written by a woman and sent to her romantic partner-->

        <paragraph n="4">We waited near the <monument>Statue of Liberty</monument> until midnight—a
            rumor had it that a "personage" was to come on board. This individual was shrouded in
            mystery until we put to sea when it was given out that the party which had clambered
            aboard in the night was none other than the Italian Mission. Our spirits rose at once
            for, what with <person name="Frank Sayre">Frank Sayre</person> on the boat and these
            distinguished Italian gentlemen, we shall doubtless be honored by a bigger convoy and so
            doubly safe. However, thus far we have but two destroyers following us. They can be seen
            distinctly outlined against the horizon, one on each side, and seem to be the same
            somber gray which all ships are affecting in this war. A sailor informed me this morning
            that we weren't in much danger for the first four or five days but that after that I
            might see some excitement. Here's hoping!</paragraph>

        <paragraph n="5">I have a small inside cabin and my <person name="unnamed Haitian room-mate"
                >room-mate</person> is quite a character. She is a native of Haiti, voluble and very
            portly—has four large pieces of baggage in our tiny stateroom, wears a costume which
            resembles a Mother Hubbard and smokes countless thin cigarettes that smell like incense!
            When I appeared, there didn't seem to be much room for me but, as she says, luckily I am
            small, and I was soon tucked into the upper berth with my belongings! She really isn't
            bad and after looking me over carefully told me that she didn't think we would fight and
            from that time has beamed upon me! She is going over to join her son who has been
            fighting with the French since the beginning of the war but will never go back to the
            Front now, having lost some fingers off each hand. She is so thankful, she says, that he
            hasn't lost more than his fingers. </paragraph>

        <source>[Source: _Canteening Overseas_: 1917-1919, published 1920.]</source>

    </letter>

    <letter sender="Marian Baldwin" recipient="unnamed loved one">
        <header>En route from <location name="Bordeaux">Bordeaux</location> to <location
                name="Paris">Paris</location>, <date when="7/18/1917"><month when="July"
                    >July</month> 18th, <year when="1917">1917</year>.</date></header>


        <paragraph n="1">On landing yesterday I went straight to the <location
                name="Hôtel de France">Hôtel de France</location> and it certainly was good to have
            room to turn around in: as for a bed with real springs I greeted it with enthusiasm!
            Towards evening <person name="Frank Sayre">Frank</person> and I took a long walk about
            the city. A port town always interests me and we saw it all at the loveliest time of
            day. The harbor was full of fishing smacks and small craft of all kinds and exquisite
            tones in the sails and rigging. The last rays of the sun cast a rosy hue over
            everything, making one think at once of <location name="Venice">Venice</location> and
            the days before the war. Later we wandered through some of the oldest parts of <location
                name="Bordeaux">Bordeaux</location> and I really felt that I was abroad again! The
            narrow winding streets and cobblestones, with here and there an ancient façade or
            doorway and everywhere, in the poorest alleys, a bit of a vine or potted plant in the
            windows. How do they manage to make it all so picturesque and alluring?</paragraph>
        <!--In the prior paragraph, the identification of 'Frank' as Frank Sayre is presumptious. It is possible the author is talking of a different Frank.-->

        <paragraph n="2">The women and the old men are doing everything and it is surprising to see
            the lady conductors. On this train they use women entirely, even in the dining car. The
            war hasn't robbed them of vivacity or their beautiful complexions and I believe they are
            even prettier in their simple black working clothes than before.</paragraph>

        <paragraph n="3">We are at present passing through the famous vineyards and I have never
            seen the country look so beautiful. The crops seem in perfect condition, thanks to the
            patient labor of these wonderful women, and the grain waves in profusion everywhere. I
            have longed for you at every turn, how you would enjoy it all. The poppies are in their
            prime and, as the train whirls by, they look like immense splashes of red
                -<simile>almost like stains of blood</simile> against the gold of the
            wheat.</paragraph>

        <paragraph n="4">I have just come in from a very excellent meal in the dining car -the food
            was served promptly by two French girls of the peasant type and with a speed that was
            wonderful, the car holding over thirty persons.</paragraph>

        <location name="Paris">Paris</location>
    </letter>

    <letter sender="Marian Baldwin" recipient="unnamed loved one">
        <header><location name="Baccarat">Baccarat</location>, <date when="7/24/1918"><month
                    when="July">July</month> 24th, <year when="1918">1918</year></date>.</header>

        <paragraph n="1">A wonderful moon to-night and the countryside transformed under its silvery
            radiance. We have had terrible nights for a week now and we are all more or less worn
            out with little sleep and long hot days. The German planes have been coming over as
            regularly as clock work and as this sector is unimportant compared to others farther up
            the line, we aren't really protected at all. An English aëroplane field lies some miles
            in the country behind us and they do what they can to help drive off the enemy planes
            but they aren't able to accomplish much as they have a huge area to cover and very
            little equipment.</paragraph>

        <paragraph n="2">I thought I knew what an air raid was like after being in <location
                name="Paris">Paris</location> for six months, but in comparison, those raids seem
            like mere child's play. Ever since the moon was two days old, the Germans haven't missed
            a single night and as soon as it gets dark, we hear the ominous whirr. At once the peace
            and quiet evaporate as if by magic and the whole atmosphere becomes alive with
            expectation and silent fears. The church bell is set ringing furiously and the doleful
            sirens begin their wailing from several parts of the town at once. Windows are thrown
            open and people begin to call back and forth to each other. This lasts only a few
            moments and then complete and utter silence. Every one has gone below ground and the
            town lies waiting in the moonlight.</paragraph>

        <paragraph n="3">At first I refused to take refuge "<translation language="French"
                translatedText="in the cellar">dans la cave</translation>" (the cellar) partly
            because I didn't want to be smothered to death beneath the plaster and brick walls of
            the house. A direct hit seemed infinitely preferable to that, also, strange as it may
            seem, I had no desire to get out of bed. I had lost so much sleep and had been working
            so hard, that night generally found me thankful for a bed. Even if the noise of guns
            kept me awake I could rest, and the moist, chilly cellar held no charms! However, I
            found that staying "<translation language="French" translatedText="in bed">au
                lit</translation>" in the midst of an air raid was unheard of in these parts and
                <person name="Madame M.">Madame M.</person> rushed into my room and with tears in
            her eyes implored me to accompany her below. The poor little old lady fears the avions
            above all else and the sound of their motors drives her into a frenzy of fear. In order
            to calm her I threw on a few clothes and we stumbled down the narrow stairs and spent
            the dark hours huddled in a little group around a candle that sputtered and flickered in
            the draughty, damp air. Our party consists always of Madame, <person name="Joséphine"
                >Joséphine</person>, <person name="unnamed French officer">a French
            officer</person>, who is likewise billeted in the house, and myself. The first night
            that we spent in the cellar, he was already below when we ladies arrived. I have never
            seen a more droll figure and I wonder now how I ever kept my face straight. He was
            attired in pink and white pajamas and on his head at a jaunty angle sat his most dressy
            uniform cap covered with gold braid and pale blue broadcloth! Undoubtedly he felt it
            added dignity and a certain modesty to his appearance. As we came down he was pacing up
            and down the mud floor in his bare feet! He told me that he had been through four years
            of war, had seen comrades blown to atoms right beside him. "I know what these bombs can
            do, I have seen with my two eyes, it is folly not to seek shelter in a raid, so when I
            hear the Boches coming, I leap from my bed <translation language="French"
                translatedText="and I run away">et je me sauve</translation>, Mademoiselle." I felt
            that he was right and that the French must be thinking some of us very children who are
            still taking war as a game, and looking upon our folly and daring as bravery. Surely no
            one has any business to waste his life. For the first and perhaps the last time our
            lives are infinitely important and useful.</paragraph>

        <paragraph n="4"><person name="unnamed French officer">This officer</person> is really a
            very good sort and entertains us during the long hours with tales of all sorts. We
            discuss the war at great length and try and keep our minds occupied and off of the
            terrible sounds overhead. It's great for my French and I am improving. Sometimes the
            noise is deafening, the anti-air-craft guns keep up a continuous fire and yet the
            Germans don't seem to be the least bit daunted and fly just above the tops of the trees,
            placing their bombs with the most pitiless accuracy. Last night three houses in this
            neighborhood were hit and in the old mill, half a block away, a young woman and her
            little girl were killed. It was a ghastly few hours. <person name="Madame M."
                >Madame</person> had one fit of hysterics right after another and threw herself
            about the cellar in a spasm of fear, trembling violently and moaning and crying. It was
            one of the most pathetic and terrible sights I have ever seen. We tried to quiet her but
            as the bombs were literally falling all about us, there wasn't much one could say to
            cheer her. When one plane had dropped its supply of horror it would dash back and in ten
            minutes another would be swooping and sailing above us and the crash and uproar would
            begin again. In order that they may see better to do their hideous work, they drop a
            flare which illuminates the town as though it were day. By the time the strong light has
            burned itself out several bombs can be neatly placed.</paragraph>

        <paragraph n="5">The raid generally begins about nine o'clock and the planes come over in
            rapid succession until dawn. It is extraordinary what an effect the sound of the German
            motor has upon one. The noise even at a great distance will wake me out of a sound sleep
            whereas our own planes can fly right past my window and I never know it.</paragraph>

        <paragraph n="6">This morning the town is really upset. Last night's raid was the worst yet.
            Two of our soldiers in the <location name="Evacuation Hospital">Evacuation
                Hospital</location> were killed and a great number of French. A bomb lit across the
            street from <location name="Y-station">the Y</location> and this morning I found all my
            canteen windows smashed into a thousand pieces. The Boches dropped several notes all
            over the streets written in French which said "If you think last night's raid a bad one,
            wait for to-night. We will break all records." The consequence is that the morale is not
            very good, every one worn out with no sleep, horror piled on horror, and the
            anticipation of worse things to-night.</paragraph>
        <!--The identification of 'the Y' as a Y-Station in the prior paragraph is presumptious. Y-stations, parts of a British information-gathering network, were commonplace in WWII, there were over 600. However, no mention to a Baccarat Y-station is easily found.-->

        <date when="7/24/1918 later">Later -Same day.</date>

        <paragraph n="7">To-day is a sizzler, quite the worse we've had. The dust pours in at the
            windows and the canteen is black with flies. We've been making lemonade for hundreds of
            hot, tired soldiers. They come in white with dust and the perspiration running down
            their cheeks. No cotton uniforms to be issued this summer; the boys have to wear their
            woolly winter ones, poor darlings, and can't even take their blouses off. The result is
            that if this weather continues the entire <acronym meaing="American Expeditiary Forces"
                >A. E. F.</acronym> will be reduced to a grease spot!</paragraph>

        <paragraph n="8">We have made a hundred and sixty liters of lemonade to-day; the canteen has
            been jammed to the doors since early morning with men, tongues hanging out and
            clammering for something "cold and wet." The boys stand around in a huge ring while we
            make the lemonade, offering all kinds of advice and suggestions; I have quite a time
            keeping them on the other side of the counter; they all want to help but we can't use
            more than three stalwart and professional lemon squeezers! When the huge tank is finally
            filled, there are loud cheers from all present and it is worth anything to see the gusto
            with which they dispatch the lemonade down their dusty throats.</paragraph>

        <paragraph n="9">How I love this place, -it's perfectly great being attached to a
            division.</paragraph>

        <paragraph n="10"><person name="Westy">Westy</person>, <person name="Alice">Alice</person>,
                <person name="Squibby">Squibby</person>, who have canteens in little villages
            nearby, are in here quite frequently and we compare notes and discuss methods, and our
            various problems at length. I imagine some of us will shortly be sent back to <location
                name="Aix-en-Provence">Aix</location> as our month of change is nearing its end. I
            can't tell you how I hate the thought of leaving, although of course I want to be where
            I am most needed. The simplicity of this place is a great contrast to Aix and does
            appeal to me so much more than the gay whirl down there with the Casino and all its
            marble halls and broad terraces. There the boys come and go and you do all you can to
            cheer them, but here they aren't on leave and are up against the real thing, and, if
            possible, need a bit of feminine companionship more than anywhere else. Also one belongs
            to a unit and after a while you come to feel a very distinct sense of proprietorship,
            your hopes and fears and special prayers are centered about the men of your outfit and
            their failures and successes are very much your own. O! I do hope that the Y will let me
            stay right where I am. I have made up my mind of course to be a good soldier whatever
            comes, but I am hoping, hoping hard every minute that I shall be allowed to
            stay.</paragraph>
        <!--The Y is mentioned again in the prior paragraph, seemingly in reference to a company or employer as pertains to the author. It is unclear if she is referencing a Y-station.-->
    </letter>

</root>
